One of the benefits of index investing
is supposed to be broad diversification,
but right now 36% of the S&P 500 index
consists of just seven stocks. If we
look at the total US market, that number
is 32%. That is the most extreme level
of index concentration in US market
history going back to 1927.
US stock market valuations are also
nearing their 1999 peaks, which were of
course followed by a decade of flat at
best US stock returns.
I get it. This does seem concerning. If
that handful of stocks declines in
value, the effect on the overall market
could be substantial. This is a movie we
have seen before up here in Canada. In
July of the year 2000, one stock made up
about 36% of the entire Canadian market
index, subsequently crashing, eventually
becoming worthless, and dragging the
market down with it. The good news is
that mitigating the worst of these
situations is not actually that hard.
I'm Ben Felix, chief investment officer
at PWL Capital, and I'm going to tell
you how to prepare for the aftermath of
the AI bubble.
[Music]
All right, I've got to come clean up
front. I don't actually know if there is
an AI bubble. Nobody does. That's only
knowable in hindsight. That being said,
some wild stuff has been happening in
the US stock market. Companies have been
spending at a blistering rate to build
out the infrastructure needed to
capitalize on the supposed AI
revolution. This type of spending often
coincides with the development of
revolutionary technologies. Railroad and
internet stocks followed a similar path
of high asset prices, massive
investment, and an eventual painful fall
in asset prices, which we might describe
as a bubble after the fact. Stock price
bubbles or periods of unusually high
stock prices followed by much lower
prices are an age-old feature of
financial markets. They are often, but
not always, sparked by some new
technology that promises huge profits
for those developing it. The history of
technology bubbles goes back to at least
the 1700s and has followed a similar
pattern with each successive major
technological innovation. In this video,
I want to talk about the two main
features of the current US market which
seem to be causing some investors to
worry. One is market valuations, the
other is market concentration. These are
two loosely related measures. Market
valuations measure how expensive it is
to buy the expected future earnings of
companies, and market concentration
measures how concentrated the market's
total value is in a small number of
stocks. High market valuations are
generally associated with a lower future
returns, while market concentration has
a much noisier relationship, if there's
any relationship at all. Market
valuations and market concentration may
both increase around the development of
new technologies simply due to the fact
that as some companies rise in value due
to their association with the new
technology, they will make up a larger
portion of the market. Bubbles are
exciting on the way up, often inducing
FOMO, fear of missing out, that may
further feed into the bubble dynamics,
and then they are painful on the way
down, both psychologically and often
economically or financially for the
people who invested in them. Bubbles are
not all bad, though. High stock prices
that arise from speculation about the
profitability of a revolutionary
technology can help to facilitate that
technology's development and deployment
into the economy. Classic examples are
the massive spending on installing fiber
optic cables in the late '90s and on
installing railway track in the 1840s.
In both cases, many of the companies
involved were able to raise a ton of
money and achieve temporarily high stock
prices as excited investors piled in,
but their share prices subsequently
crashed. Bubbles do tend to come with
waste, too much unused fiber optic
cable, too much redundant railway track,
but despite the waste, the
infrastructure for the respective
technologies does get created, paving
the way for a potential economic golden
age to follow. These productive bubbles
are probably on net a good thing for the
economy, even if they can be painful for
investors. The pattern of investor
excitement and high stock prices
surrounding technological revolutions or
potential technological revolutions goes
back hundreds of years, and it always
follows this similar path. Stock prices
are driven up by some combination of
high profit potential from the
revolutionary technology, and once it
starts rising, speculation that the
associated stocks will continue rising.
Eventually, prices do come back to
earth, resulting in a low returns for
anyone who bought near the top. Whether
that's what we're seeing in the US right
now, again, can only be known in
hindsight. Prices could remain high. The
rapid rise in prices of the top US
stocks has also been accompanied by
rapid earnings growth. It's not pure
hype. There is some economic substance
here. What we do know is that a large
portion of the US market's return,
earnings growth, and capital expenditure
has come from AI-related stocks since
the launch of ChatGPT. A September 2025
report from JP Morgan explains that
AI-related stocks have accounted for 75%
of S&P 500 returns, 80% of earnings
growth, and 90% of capital spending
growth since ChatGPT launched in
November 2022.
We also know that US stock market
concentration, which was already high,
has shot up even further. Stock market
concentration and high stock valuations
are, again, different issues, but they
can be related by the fact that a rapid
rise in valuations for a small number of
firms can also lead to market
concentration. To be completely clear,
in case I wasn't already, I am not
taking a position on whether we are
witnessing a bubble in the US stock
market, but I think it's useful to look
at past instances of high stock market
valuations and market concentration to
understand the potential implications
and lessons. The Canadian example that I
mentioned earlier is even more extreme
than what we're currently seeing in the
US market. Northern Electric and
Manufacturing Co. was spun off from Bell
Canada in 1895.
In 1998, it was renamed Nortel Networks.
During the dot-com bubble, Nortel's
early work in optical networking
technologies propelled it to the
forefront of the internet infrastructure
revolution. It was making truly useful
stuff that the world needed or thought
it needed. Its stock price soared,
creating huge amounts of wealth for
investors and for the many employees who
received stock-based compensation.
Incredibly, the company peaked at over
36% of the Canadian stock market index,
at the time called the TSE 300. Nortel,
and thus the Canadian stock market, had
extremely high valuations in August of
the year 2000, peaking at a Shiller
cyclically adjusted price-earnings ratio
of 60.6, far surpassing the peak
valuation of the US stock market during
the same dot-com period. The Shiller
cyclically adjusted price-earnings ratio
measures market prices against the
index's 10-year average real historical
earnings, on the assumption that
long-term earnings growth tends to be
steady. A high Shiller PE means that
investors are paying a lot more for
future earnings and should therefore
expect lower future returns, unless
earnings end up being unusually high in
the future, which can happen.
Nortel's downfall started with a string
of unprofitable internet-related
acquisitions and was accelerated by the
dot-com bubble popping. The result for
the Canadian stock market was
devastating. The Canadian TSE 300 index
dropped by 43% between September 2000
and September 2002. That obviously
hurts. There are two lessons that I
think are important to explain here.
First, well this drop was definitely
painful, I don't want to minimize that,
the market recovered by July 2005, and
it went on to deliver strong returns,
while the US market, as I'll detail in a
minute, struggled for more than a
decade. Despite having been more
concentrated, the Canadian market was
more resilient than the US market. The
Nortel crash was, in hindsight, a short
blip in a long track record of strong
performance for Canadian stocks. Second,
while the Canadian market as a whole was
hurt by its exposure to Nortel, Canadian
value stocks, a Canadian value stock
index, so stocks with low prices
relative to their fundamentals, did not
crash when the overall market did, and
it actually delivered even stronger
returns than the market on the recovery.
This will come up again in my next
examples, too. The US market did not
have such extreme concentration in 1999
as it does today or as Canada did back
then, but it did have high stock prices,
which were, in hindsight, mostly
unjustified by fundamentals. Some
companies like Microsoft and Amazon came
through the other side and proved that
there was real transformational
potential in the internet, but the vast
majority of companies that tried to
capitalize on the internet failed. This
led to the famous dot-com bubble and the
subsequent lost decade for US stocks.
The US market crashed starting around
March of 2000, and measured in Canadian
dollar terms, remained flat or below
flat until July of 2013. That is another
brutal period of technology-induced high
prices, leading to the low realized
stock returns for investors who bought
at the peak. In this case, unlike with
Nortel, the recovery was not so swift.
Part of the problem is that the great
financial crisis intervened as stock
prices were starting to recover. Either
way, this technology bust was painful
for US investors, or investors in US
stocks, in general, and even more so for
investors focused on US technology
stocks. It would have taken them even
longer to recover.
Similar to the Canadian example, an
investor in US value stocks, and to an
even greater extent US small-cap value
stocks, fared much better over this long
period of poor performance for the
market as a whole. They earned positive
returns while the market was flat at
best for an extended period of time.
It's also worth reiterating that
Canadian stocks performed reasonably
well over this period. Diversification
is known as the only free lunch in
investing for good reason. The main
problem with diversification is
behavioral. It inherently means that you
always own the stuff that's performing
well and the stuff that's performing
poorly, which is not always so easy to
do. Okay, so these two examples, the
Canadian and the US example, they had
high market valuations in common, but
the Canadian market became much more
concentrated than the US market.
In the past, the US market has reached
high concentration levels without going
on to deliver poor future returns. Not
quite as high as today, but still high.
I looked at this within the US market
going back to 1926. I sorted 10-year
future returns on the starting level of
market concentration in the top seven
stocks. There's a very slight negative
correlation between market concentration
and future returns, but it's not
statistically significant, meaning
there's a good chance it's just noise in
the data. But statistical significance
aside, it's still a weak relationship
economically. A point that often seems
to get lost in discussions of the US
market's concentration is that many
other markets around the world are far
more concentrated. I mean, I gave you
guys the Canada example, and yet they
still managed to deliver positive
returns, in some cases even more so than
the US market. Looking back at the last
10 years of returns, just as an example,
the weight of the top seven stocks in
the 10 largest stock markets, excluding
the US, was 40.94%.
So, higher than the US.
In November 2015, so we're looking back
10 years in history. Switzerland was the
most concentrated market at 60.11%
in the top seven stocks, and Japan was
the least concentrated at 16.91%.
The return from November 1st, 2015 to
November 26, 2025, measured in USD, was
8.44% on average for all of these
countries. That does trail the US market
return, but still delivers a
meaningfully positive equity risk
premium. Taiwan was one of the most
concentrated markets in November 2015,
and it outperformed the US market over
the subsequent 10-year period. The
overall relationship between market
concentration and future returns across
countries seems to be noisy at best.
An interesting, sort of anecdotal
perspective is AT&T, which was broken up
into smaller companies starting in 1982.
It was the largest company in the US
market at that time and in prior
decades, not when it was broken up, but
in prior decades, it made up a larger
portion of the US market than Nvidia
makes up today. The interesting question
is, was the US market less risky after
the breakup? I think that would be
pretty hard to argue. You could maybe
even argue the opposite.
Something that does appear in the data,
at least post-1950, is the returns can
suffer over periods where concentration
is falling. I think this again makes
sense. If concentration comes from
rising valuations for a handful of
firms, falling valuations for those
firms would lead to lagging returns.
But even then, we're talking about less
positive returns, not a total disaster.
The relationship between market
valuations and future returns is
stronger, at least economically, both
across markets and within the US market.
To illustrate this, I looked at the
relationship between the starting
cyclically adjusted price-earnings
ratio, the CAPE ratio, and the 10-year
return for the 10 largest developed
stock markets going back to 1982. I
looked at rolling periods with a 1-month
step. I acknowledge that there are
potential problems with this setup, like
difficulties in comparing the CAPE ratio
across countries, and from a statistical
perspective, the fact that I'm using
these overlapping samples, the rolling
periods of the 1-month step, it does
make any conclusions drawn from the data
statistically questionable. Now, that
being said, there is a clear monotonic
relationship between starting cyclically
adjusted price-earnings ratio, so
starting valuations, and future 10-year
returns. When the CAPE ratio is higher
at the start, future returns are lower.
Again, this does not mean that the
market must crash tomorrow or next week
when valuations are high, but it might
mean that it makes sense to moderate our
expectations for future returns from the
US market in particular due to its
currently elevated valuations.
The Japanese stock market had a crazy
run leading up to 1990, eventually
becoming the largest stock market in the
world by market capitalization,
surpassing even the US market for a
period of time. Japan was viewed as this
unstoppable economic powerhouse, and its
stock market valuations reached levels
rarely seen elsewhere in history.
I'm not saying the US is today's Japan,
but I think it's an important example to
think about. At the end of 1989, the
Japanese market did crash. So, it had
these crazy high valuations, and then it
prices do start to come down. The market
really does crash.
The crazy thing about the Japan example,
though, is that it has not recovered in
real terms, so if we adjust for
inflation, to this day. So, it crashes
in the end of the end of 1989, and now
we're in almost 2026. And if you adjust
for inflation, the Japanese market is
still not recovered from the crash, or
it's it's flat
after the crash.
Now, two things would have saved an
investor in Japanese stocks in 1989.
Diversification across markets, a
globally diversified investor did just
fine as the US market kind of took the
torch of stock market dominance back
from Japan with a a vengeance. The US
went on to absolutely uh perform
exceptionally well, as Japan had done
previously.
And then the other thing that would have
helped is diversification within the
Japanese market itself. Despite Japan's
stock market struggles over this long
period of time, as with my previous
examples, Japanese value and small-cap
value stocks have actually performed
fine over this period.
Now, again, this does not mean that I'm
suggesting getting out of the US stock
market. I we could have had a very
similar conversation to what we're
having now in 2021 when US market
valuations were high again.
Uh not quite as high as today, but still
high. Uh that would have been a mistake.
US stock returns have continued to be
very positive since then.
But what it does mean is not expecting
the same rocket-ship returns that the US
market has been delivering to continue
forever. The US stock market currently
has these two defining features that are
causing some investors to worry: high
stock valuations and high market
concentration. Market concentration,
while seemingly problematic due to the
potential impact of a few large firms
faltering and bringing the market down
with them, has not historically been as
much of an issue as you might expect.
Anecdotally, the Canadian market
recovered from extreme period of market
concentration and high valuations during
the dot-com bust more quickly than the
less concentrated US market. Looking
more broadly at the 10 largest non-US
stock markets for the last 10 years, the
relationship between concentration and
future returns is seemingly nonexistent.
Looking at US returns from 1927 to 2024,
there is a weak economic relationship
that is not statistically significant
between market concentration and future
returns. Stock market valuations, on the
other hand, are more impactful, and that
is another concerning aspect of the US
market right now.
High current valuations, while not a
perfect predictor of future returns, do
seem to be at least somewhat related.
This relationship, while it's
economically strong, doesn't really hold
up to statistical scrutiny for the
simple reason that we don't have that
many independent samples to draw
conclusions from. Past market valuations
tell us only a little bit about the
future. It's always possible, as the US
market has demonstrated in recent
history, for high valuations to be
followed by high returns and continued
high valuations.
Even if history tells us that that isn't
an unlikely outcome, it is what we have
seen.
The main lessons from the information in
this video, I think, are diversification
and discipline, which I think are
related. A properly diversified investor
should be comfortable sticking with
their portfolio through good times and
bad, knowing they will always hold the
losers. You have to accept that.
Whatever's not doing well, if you're
diversified, you probably own that.
But you also own the winners. And people
who are comfortable with their
investment strategy understand that the
winners that they own are going to have
an edge over the losers in the long run,
which is something that has been
true throughout history. Thanks for
watching. I'm Ben Felix, Chief
Investment Officer at PWR Capital. If
you enjoyed this video, please share it
with someone in your life who's
concerned about the AI bubble.